San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company collection, Inclusive: 1891-1983, Bulk: 1891-1935
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company collection
Inclusive: 1891-1983, Bulk: 1891-1935
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2448
Johnson, J.O.B., 1911 - 1997
1 document box and 3 oversized boxes.
This collection contains photocopies of annual reports and timetables produced by the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company from the 1890's to the 1930's.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Originals/Duplicates
All copies.
Biography/Profile
The San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company was chartered on 1884 August 28. The railroad from San Antonio to Aransas Bay, which covered a distance of 135 miles, was designed to connect San Antonio to a large, deep-water port other than Galveston.
The railroad experienced significant growth during the late 1880s, including a line from Yoakum to Waco. By 1891, the railroad boasted 688 miles of track within the state of Texas.
Due to various lawsuits and accidents, however, the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company went into receivership in 1890 July. The Southern Pacific Railroad attempted to buy control of its competitor but was sued by the Texas Railroad Commission in 1903 for attempting to own “parallel and competing lines.” By 1925, the Southern Pacific Railroad was permitted to buy the SA&AP outright.
J.O.B. Johnson, the creator and donor of this collection, spent many years collecting materials pertaining to the history of the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company. John Oscar Birgen (J.O.B.) Johnson was born in Travis County, Texas on April 18, 1911. At the age of 25, Johnson moved to Waco where he became a machinist for the Missouri-Kansas-Texas Railroad. He was also a railroad enthusiast, collecting vast amounts of personal research and serving with various historical societies including the Central Texas Chapter of the National Railway Historical Society. Johnson passed away in Waco in 1997.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials related to the operation of the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company. The documents range from 1891 to 1983, but the bulk of the materials cover the time period between 1891 and 1935.
Series I. Annual Reports is comprised exclusively of annual reports produced by the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company. Some of these documents are more generic in nature, but the majority are complex information packets submitted annually by the company to the Texas Railroad Commission. This series is the largest series in the collection.
Series II. Literary Productions consists of timetables created by the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company in addition to reports produced by the U.S. Interstate Commerce Commission.
All of the materials in the collection are photocopies obtained by donor J.O.B. Johnson and are in excellent condition.
Arrangement
Prior to the current round of processing, the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company collection was housed in folders with basic descriptions and dates. A detailed item-level inventory was produced at the time of donation in 1993 June.
The collection is now arranged according to material type and consists of two series: I. Annual Reports and II. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2448. Acquired 1983-08-31
Related Resources
Items in related collections
John Oscar Birgen "Swede" Johnson papers, Inclusive: 1860s-1990s
National Railway Historical Society: Central Texas Chapter records, Inclusive: 1887-1983, undated, Bulk: 1982-1983, undated
Related references
Hemphill, Hugh. “San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railroad.” Accessed 2017 June 9.
"Obituary of J. O. Birgen Johnson." Waco Tribune-Herald. 1997 July 28.
Young, Nancy Beck. “San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2017 June 9.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company -- Records and correspondence -- Facsimiles.; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission -- Records and correspondence -- Facsimiles.
Subjects
Railroads -- Texas -- Timetables -- Facsimiles.
- Annual Reports, 1891-1933; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. Annual Reports is the largest series in the collection. It consists exclusively of annual reports produced by the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company between 1891 and 1933. Some of the annual reports are more generic, but the bulk of the materials are copies of annual report packets submitted annually by the company to the Texas Railroad Commission. The latter reports contain a wide range of information about the railroad including officers, stock, equipment, incomes, expenses, and mileage.
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company, 1895 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company, 1899 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company, 1908 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company, 1915 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1915 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1916 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1916 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1917 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission (1 of 2), 1918 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission (2 of 2), 1918 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission (1 of 2), 1919 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission (2 of 2), 1919 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1920 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1921 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1891 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1893 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1898 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1899 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1900 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1901 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1903 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 7)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1904 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 8)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1905 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 9)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1909 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 10)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1910 June 30 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 11)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1911 June 30 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1912 June 30 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1913 June 30 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1914 June 30 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1922 December 31 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1923 December 31 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1924 December 31 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 7)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1925 April 30 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 8)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1925 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1926 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1927 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1928 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1929 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1930 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1931 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 7)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1932 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 8)
  - San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company: Texas Railroad Commission, 1933 December 31 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 9)
- Literary Productions, 1893-1983; 2
  Series II. Literary Productions contains decisions reported by the United States Interstate Commerce Commission, timetables created by the San Antonio and Aransas Pass Railway Company, and an article from a June 1983 issue of Texas Railroads.
  - Appendix: Texas Railroads, 1983 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Decisions: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1924 October-1925 April (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Decisions: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1926 September-November (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Decisions: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1930 June-October (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Decisions: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1931 May-1932 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Decisions: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1933 April-December (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Decisions: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1935 February-October (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Timetable, 1893 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Timetable, 1902 October 5 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 10)
  - Timetable, 1924 November 1 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 11)